<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[CostCarbon]]></title><description><![CDATA[Theory for Economic Change. Addressing Warming, Waste & Want]]></description><link>https://www.costcarbon.org/home</link><generator>RSS for Node</generator><lastBuildDate>Fri, 17 Nov 2023 04:31:25 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.costcarbon.org/blog-feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title><![CDATA[A double challenge and double sided solution.]]></title><description><![CDATA[Our existing linear, economy has evolved over thousands of years in phases first from hunter gatherers to farming communities, then...]]></description><link>https://www.costcarbon.org/post/a-double-challenge-and-double-sided-solution</link><guid isPermaLink="false">63b65fd764f33f8197912fee</guid><pubDate>Thu, 05 Jan 2023 05:30:15 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/6d9349_8f2d6e34a24148b1afbe7a61c881c761~mv2.png/v1/fit/w_1000,h_1000,al_c,q_80/file.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><dc:creator>Louis </dc:creator><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Our existing linear, economy has evolved over thousands of years in phases first from hunter gatherers to farming communities, then bartering and trading and early forms of currency; shells, grain then silver and gold, then coins and promissory notes and today, fiat currency and digital currency. With each development we have moved further from our connection and 'coupling' with nature. </p>
<p>We have progressively decoupled the price of things from human and natural constraints. Today the social  value and cost to nature are not reflected in the price. The common transaction of our modern economy disconnects the production and supply side from demand and consumption side, meaning the consumer has little or not visibility of the prior implications of the choices they make. These implications are externalised from the transaction with the resulting ‘un-costed’ emissions, waste and inequality. </p>

<p>Our current economy has two major problems:</p><ol>
  <li>The externalities of every transaction between buyer and seller create a significant amount of waste that remains largely unaddressed. This waste represents a huge opportunity for growth, as it can be converted into wealth. The linear economy systemically relies on waste.  Material waste after first use is at 90%, energy at 60% and food at 40%. By addressing this waste, we have the potential to achieve material resource abundance, social well-being, and to restore a balance between humanity and nature. We define waste as lost or latent value. </li>
  <li>Consumers are unaware of the social and environmental impact of their purchasing decisions or the value that is lost as a result. Oscar Wilde said, "The cynic knows the price of everything and the value of nothing," while Warren Buffet stated, "Price is what you pay. Value is what you get. Price and value are two sides of the same coin." However this relationship between price and value assumes ignorance of cost. In order to understand the potential value or true price of something, we must be informed of the cost. Cost refers to the resources (such as time, energy, materials, information, and labor) required to produce, manufacture, or acquire a product or service. Price is the amount of money asked or charged by a seller or provider. Value is the worth or importance placed on something by consumers and is subjective, based on individual needs, preferences, and circumstances.  Value is the benefit, utility, and well-being derived from a product or service. Neither price nor value can be independent of cost.</li>
</ol><p>To make informed choices, consumers require a transparent understanding of the relationship between price, cost, and value. This calls for systems that treat both sides of transactions coherently, equitably and transparently.</p>

<p>In a linear economy, energy, material, and information have a beginning and an end. Ultimately the linear economy is a system that depends on the source, use, consumption, and waste of these inputs, it is a terminal one where the energy, material, and information are unrecoverable and lost. This is not compatible within a resource constrained environment; our planet Earth!</p>

<p>In a circular economy, we are all both consumers and producers; we are custodians or stewards in a regenerative and perpetuating material and energy cycle. Regardless of our role within the energy and material cycle, we are the recipients of the material inputs, we utilise them and they are passed on to the next </p>

<p>The concept of the "invisible hand," which refers to the self-regulating nature of free markets guided by selfish interests, has no place in a regenerative economy. Today our economy must be regenerative by design, for biodiversity, resilience and the well-being of our species. </p>

<p>Waste is lost and latent value that represents a +90% growth opportunity that will restore a balance between humanity and nature.</p><figure><img src="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/6d9349_8f2d6e34a24148b1afbe7a61c881c761~mv2.png/v1/fit/w_1000,h_1000,al_c,q_80/file.png"  ></figure><p>That is the design and purpose of the CostCarbon initiative. </p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[The urgency for action]]></title><description><![CDATA[By the end of 2020's we must reduce our emissions by half in order to avoid exceeding 2+ degrees of warming. Unfortunately, the current...]]></description><link>https://www.costcarbon.org/post/the-urgency-for-action</link><guid isPermaLink="false">63b5136cd1ddc4243ee51566</guid><pubDate>Wed, 04 Jan 2023 05:49:35 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/6d9349_7c6f1132a7b949ceb015f2b94a4e2e12~mv2.png/v1/fit/w_1000,h_1000,al_c,q_80/file.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><dc:creator>Louis </dc:creator><content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>By the end of 2020's we must reduce our emissions by half in order to avoid exceeding 2+ degrees of warming. </p>
<p>Unfortunately, the current pace of change towards net zero emissions is not sufficient to meet this goal. </p>
<p>Governments, businesses, and other organisations have not been meeting the commitments made in previous decades to address climate change. </p>
<p>We need a different approach to accelerate change and empower individuals to take action and 'own' the change. </p>
<p>Our humanity is our common denominator!</p>
<p>Businesses and governments are collectives of individuals, making decisions for different motives but at the end of the day we all have similar needs, aspirations, family and friends who we love and are answerable to. </p>
<p>We need ways to make meaningful change and we also need governance frameworks and systems that recognise both; the urgency of the existential threat of climate change and also our agency as individuals and in communities.</p>
<p>Everyone has a role to play in addressing climate change. </p>
<p>CostCarbon goal is to give everyone the ability to take direct action to address the issue. </p>
<p>We propose a system that distinguishes between good and bad practices, reverses the loss of value in material flow cycles, and distributes opportunities and outcomes more fairly. </p>
<p>In order to stop global warming and protect democracy for future generations, we need the collective action of people all over the world. </p>
<p>Join us and be part of the solution.</p><figure><img src="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/6d9349_7c6f1132a7b949ceb015f2b94a4e2e12~mv2.png/v1/fit/w_1000,h_1000,al_c,q_80/file.png"  ></figure>]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>